FRIENDS OF THE LIBRARIES RECORDS, (UA-580.20.01), 1981-2006
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Friends of the Libraries Records 1981-2006
3.3 cubic ft.
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
The Friends of the Libraries Records contain the day-to-day activities of this University at Albany organization comprised of faculty, staff, alumni, and community members. The collection includes agendas, minutes, correspondence, scrapbooks, and community outreach materials.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Anne Roberts, University Library Liason to the Friends of the Library, initially donated the scrapbooks in 1989. Former President Ben-Ami Lipetz donated the majority of remaining materials in 2006.
Organizational History
In 1981, Anne Roberts, Assistant Director of Libraries at the University at Albany, brought together a group of faculty and staff interested in supporting the libraries and this group formally became the Friends of the Libraries the following year. The group welcomed alumni, community residents, current and retired faculty members, and anyone interested in the future of the University Libraries. The organization sponsored gifts and donations to the University Libraries. As part of its efforts, the Friends of the Libraries preserved Dewey Library's stained glass windows and murals in the downtown campus buildings. The Friends of the Libraries created the Alice Hastings Murphy Scholarship to provide for student library employees and full-time library staff members who want to become librarians and named it for the former Director of Libraries from 1956 to 1970. The Friends of the Libraries' annual book sale every fall funded student scholarships and awards.
The Friends of the Libraries also promoted community outreach. It held open talks called “Wednesday Wanderings” where professors and local, prominent figures spoke about Albany’s history, their own research, and other interesting topics. The organization also went on historic outings in the Capital District, Historic Hudson Valley and beyond, including Olana, Hyde Park, Mohonk Mountain House, Lake George, and the Glimmerglass Opera.
The Friends of the Libraries remained active until 2006. Presidents included: Alice Hastings Murphy (1982-1985, 1992-1999), Ruth Abele (1985-1986), Ben-Ami Lipetz (1986-1988, 2003-2006), Kenneth Doran (1988-1992), and Charles Ciaccio (1999-2003). The Library Liasons included Anne Roberts (1981-1986, 1988), Bonita Bryant (1986-1990), Dorothy Christiansen (1989-2002), Roberta Armstrong (2002-2006), and Geoff Williams (2006).
Scope and Content Information
This collection documents the administrative records and community outreach efforts of the Friends of the Libraries. It has the organization's monthly meeting agendas and minutes as well as fliers for monthly talks, annual book sales, and materials about community outings. There are VHS tapes with recordings of talks held in conjunction with the University's celebration of its sesquicentennial.
The collection also contains two large scrapbooks that President Anne Roberts created. The scrapbooks document the Friends of the Libraries’ outreach events. These include the annual book sale as well as academic talks with prominent professors of the University, such as the History Department’s Sung Bok Kim and the Atmospheric Science Department’s Bernard Vonnegut. The scrapbooks also contain information on Friends of the Libraries outings, with photos of Olana and Sagamor as well as fliers and RSVP forms. The scrapbooks also include information about donations and library support.
Archivists transfered a monograph Experiencing Albany: Perspectives on a Grand City's Past, edited by Anne Roberts and Judith VanDyk, to the book division of Special Collections. The catalogue record for the monograph is included in Minerva, the University Library Catalog.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administrative Records, 1981-2006
Series 2 - Community Outreach, 1982-2003
Series 1 and 2 are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
State University of New York at Albany. Friends of the Libraries; State University of New York at Albany. University Libraries; State University of New York at Albany; Library fund raising--United States; Library outreach programs--United States; Friends of the library--United States; Albany (N.Y.); Agendas (administrative records); Photographs; Correspondence; Files by subject; Minutes; Scrapbooks; Budgets; Fliers (printed material)
Container List
- Series 1: Administrative Records, 1981-2006; Undated; 1.72 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains agendas and minutes of the organization from 1981 to 2006. The organization for agendas and minutes is different from 2003 to 2006 because the material came to archives in its original order. In these files, there is supplemental material along with administrative records. There are also multiple agendas for some months because President Ben-Ami Lipetz took notes on his agenda copies (any of these will make note of it in the upper right hand corner).
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Agendas, Minutes and Supplemental Materials, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Alice Murphy Scholarship, 1994; 1998; 2000; 2001 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Awards and Donations, 1982-2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Board Members, 1986-2006 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Book Bags, 1989-2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Book Marks-PR/Productions, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - "25 and Going Strong"-Booklet, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Budgets and Expenditures, 1983-2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bylaws, 1983; 1987; 1988; 1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Calendars, 1990-2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Campaign for the University Library, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Committee/Research Documents, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1981-2002 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Grants, Supporting Programs, 1983-1998 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - History, 1969; 1977; 1980-1983; Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Mailing Lists, 1987-2001 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Member card, 1985; 1988-1989; 1993-1998 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - New Hampshire Primary Talk, Kathleen Kendall, February 22, 1996 (Cassette 1)
  - Newsletter, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Notes from ACRL Session, April 21, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Potential Recruits, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Scrapbooks, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"The Residence Halls and their Impact on Student Life"-Mary Ellen Nankes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"A Monoloth from Humble Origins"-Matthew Fredrick, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Contest-"The James Allen JR. Collegiate Center: An Experiment in Undergraduate Education"-Thomas Pullyblank, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Sesquicentennial Historical Essay Award, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Sesquicentennial Program 1, February 24, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 1)
    Program is "History of the University at Albany," led by Professor Kendall Birr, Faculty, Emeritus, Department of History.
  - Sesquicentennial Program 2, March 17, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 2)
    Program is "New York State College for Teachers: The 1940s and and 1950s," led by Dr. Theodore Fossieck, Jacquelyn Mann Gavryck, Professor M.E. Grenander, Dr. Oscar E. Lanford, Professor Wallace Taylor, and Louise Hesnney Waterman.
  - Sesquicentennial Program 3, April 28, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 3)
    Program is "State University of New York at Albany: Years of Growth and Change, 1960s" led by Professor Arthur Collins, Professor Randolph Gardner, Stuart Horn, Professor Mauritz Johnson, Dr. Elmer Mathews, Alice Hastings Murphy, and Judy A. Mysliborski.
  - Sesquicentennial Program 4, September 22, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 4)
    Program is "Design and Construction of the Uptown Campus," led by Professor Raymond Bromley, Professor Edward Crowley, Professor Thomas H. Littlefield, Robert Ruckterstuhl, and Elwin Stevens.
  - Sesquicentennial Program 5, October 15, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 5)
    Program is "The University at Albany: Changing for the 1970s and 1980s," led by Professor Mark Berger, Frederick K. Brewington, Gloria DeSole, Dr. David W. Martin, Professor Joan Schulz, and Victoria Zeldin.
  - Sesquicentennial Program 6, November 17, 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Event also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 6)
    Program is "Kate Stoneman, normal School Alumna and First Woman Lawyer in New York State," led by Geoffrey Williams, University Arvhivist and Campus Records Officer.
  - Sesquicentennial Programs, 1-3, February-April 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Events also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 7)
  - Sesquicentennial Programs, 4-6, September-November 1994; Duplicate tape exists. Events also filmed from multiple camera angles. Additional video tapes depict this. (Video-tape 8)
  - Source Guide, 1994; 1995 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - "Spinning Straw into Gold: A Look at Cuesta College's Friends of the Library", September 1999 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Spring-Fall Letters, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Student Achievement Award, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Suggested Distribution List, Undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - University at Albany Perspectives, Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Series 2: Community Outreach, 1982-2003; Undated; 1.58 ft.
  This series has annual book sale promotions, brochures, outing fliers, outing photos, and left over exhibit pieces on the Friends of the Libraries. This series also has information on monthly talks that the Friends sponsored. These are called Community Conversations or Wednesday Wanderings. Speakers of these talks included prominent professors and members of the community.
  - Booksale, 1983-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brochures, 1989-1990; 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Comment and Interest Summary Cards, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Community Conversations, 1982-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Directions and Pamphlets, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Exhibit, 1990; 1993; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibit, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Glimmerglass Opera Outings, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Library Hours, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Interactive Media Center-Information Sheet and Orientation, September 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Outing Brochures, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Outings, 1984-2002; 1981-2006 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Outings and Lectures, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Outings-Taken by Jacqueline A. Gavryck-Includes Letter, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Plaque, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Proclamation, Albany, New York-Mayor Jennings, May 12, 2006 (Flat-file 1)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1982-1983 (Oversized 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1984-1986 (Oversized 2)
  - Library Tour, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - University at Albany Libraries-Updates and Progress, 1994; 1996-1998; 2001 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Volunteers, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)